[Music]
This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.
All right. All right. So, let me let me
just uh tell you what the story is with
dark
energy, big
rips, whether uh dark energy uh will
have a tendency to tear atoms apart and
so forth. Uh we're not we're
not in past classes, we've studied a
little bit about dark energy. So for
those who uh were there, I'll just
remind
you for practical
purposes, let's forget the deep story,
but for practical
purposes, dark energy or cosmological
constant or whatever you like to call
it, vacuum energy, the observed
um accelerated expansion of the
universe that is equivalent
to a small repulsive force, a component
to gravity. Now you say gravity is not
repulsive. Well, suspend judgment about
that until we get to it in this class.
Uh and imagine a small repulsive
component to gravity which is
not
proportional to 1 / r 2 like Newtonian
gravity.
But in fact where the force increases
with
distance, it increases with distance
roughly the same way. Well, how does a
uh how about a spring? Supposing you
have a
particle on a spring connected to the
wall or two particles connected by
springs. How does the force depend on
the separation between them?
The force grows linearly with a
separation between them. Of course,
until you break the spring, but let's
not break the spring. The force grows
linearly and it's proportional to the
distance between uh the
uh uh the particles at the end of the
spring. Force grows linearly. There's
some constant there usually called the
spring constant. Let's put it in. And
because it's attractive pulling the two
things together, there's a minus sign
there. Uh imagine that we have such a
spring. Okay. Now what? And with two
particles attached to it, what does the
cosmological constant do? What the
cosmological constant, the repulsive
cosmological constant, what it does, a a
positive cosmological constant or a
positive dark energy, what it does is it
adds a little
bit of force of just this type
proportional to
distance, but repulsive, not attractive.
This is attractive. That's the minus
sign there. Repulsive. So it adds a
little bit of repulsive force to uh the
otherwise attractive force between the
two particles on the end of the spring.
Now I'm not really thinking about two
particles on the end of the spring but
it's a good model for us. What I'm
really thinking of for example is uh an
atom. An atom is a system which is
composed of two or more particles held
together by forces. The forces are not
entirely different than spring forces.
But what would happen if you added to
this a little bit of much smaller than
the spring
constant? The spring constant which
holds atoms together is quite strong.
The dark energy forces are minute.
They're incredibly small until you get
very very far away. Notice this force
grows with distance. To get this one,
we're going to add now a little bit of
component. The coefficient in front of
it is called the cosmological constant
or the dark energy also times
r. What would it do to the spring if
there was a tiny tiny coefficient here?
And that coefficient is truly small uh
for ordinary laboratory experiments.
All it would do would be to change the
equilibrium position of the particles at
the ends of the spring a little bit. It
would effectively
change the spring constant here, make it
a little bit
smaller. But what would happen if you
made the spring constant a little bit
weaker? All that would happen is that
the spring with the particles on it
would be a little bit bigger. That's
all. Atoms would grow by an entirely
negligible amount. They wouldn't be torn
apart. They wouldn't be torn apart. It
would just change the equilibrium
position of the electrons in the atom by
a tiny, completely insignificant amount.
uh and that would be the net effect on
atoms. It would be the net
effect on almost anything that was
otherwise bound together. The reason is
that this lambda here, how small is it?
It's so small that this force doesn't
become significant until you get out to
the full measure of the entire global
universe. That's where it begins to get
big. But if you ask about it on the
scale of the solar system, it's
negligible. It's tiny by comparison with
the other forces in the solar system,
gravity and other things. And so what it
would do is it would change the
equilibrium position of the Earth a
little bit, a tiny tiny bit. Or it would
change the size of a galaxy a little bit
and expand it out a little bit, but it
wouldn't overcome the forces which hold
things together.
Now there's
a theory called the big
rip. It violates every principle of
physics. It does. It violates every
principle of
physics. Uh why anybody would take it
seriously, I don't know. But when
serious
theorists work out the equations and say
there are limits between this and that
such and such cannot be bigger than this
or such and such cannot be smaller than
that for deep fundamental principles.
Somebody is going to come along and say,
"Yeah, but what if those principles are
wrong and such and such can be a little
bit bigger or a little bit smaller than
the bound that the theoretical
principles tell you." Somebody will come
along and say that they'll write a paper
about it.
The paper will last for till it gets to
the New York
Times and then it will
slowly fall into the junk heap of bad
physics ideas. The big rip is one of
those ideas, but I'll tell you I'm not
going to try to tell you right now uh
what is wrong with it. We'll eventually
come to it, but it's basically the idea
that this constant lambda here is timed
dependent that it grows with time. Now,
there's no reason on earth to believe
that. Not only is there no reason on
earth to believe it, there are very,
very strong reasons on earth to
disbelieve it. But you could say, "Who
cares what theorists say?" Let's make a
prediction of what would happen if
lambda grew with time. Well, if it grew
with time,
eventually it would become stronger than
the forces which bind together other
objects.
At first it would become stronger than
the forces which hold galaxies together
and galaxies would fly apart. Then it
would become stronger than the forces
which hold the solar system apart. Solar
system would fly apart. Then eventually
it would become stronger than the forces
which hold the spring together. Spring
flies apart.
As I said, that's called the big rip.
That this constant lambda, the dark
energy is not a constant at all, but
that it increases with time. Decreases
with time is allowable. Increases with
time violates uh some strong yah. As I
interpret what you're saying, lambda is
a function of mass or whatever. No,
lambda is just a numerical constant.
Period. Well, the point I'm getting at
is what if there's no mass? Is that
lambda still in effect?
It's a force that would be there between
any pair of particles if the particles
were there. If the particles weren't
there, there wouldn't be any particles
to have a force on them. So, uh, lambda
lambda evolves with time or changes. No,
according according to most current
thinking, it's called a cosmological
constant for good reasons because all of
the good theory says it ought to be a
constant. Now, could it not be a
constant? Uh, it doesn't violate any
very very deep principles for it to
decrease with time. It violates big
principles to increase with time. So um
but we we'll come to this. I just wanted
to assure you to make you feel better
about uh the
future that dark energy is like a
huge component when you start looking at
stuff
like it's like 20%. So if it's so small
how can a huge effect you know well the
dark the dark energy density in this
room is tiny. It's extremely small. I'll
tell you how small it
is. Um, take a cubic
meter and how
many how many protons worth a proton has
a certain mass. E=
MC². So there's a certain amount of
energy in every proton.
Uh roughly speaking, I think the dark
energy in this room per cubic meter
uh would
be I would have to work it out, but it's
roughly of order about a thousand
protons. A thousand protons in a cubic
meter is a negligible amount of energy.
Its gravitational effects on things are
really negligible. But if you had it
smeared out through the entire universe
that
way, then at sufficiently big distances
away. Now imagine now, imagine now we
live in a world which has an
extra bit of energy that's causing
repulsion, but it's spread out
throughout the entire universe in a
smooth distribution.
Then eventually at sufficiently large
distances it would make an effect a
repulsive effect on things which would
become big. But those distances are
cosmological in size. So it has an
effect on the global universe but it
doesn't have an effect on certainly not
on laboratory physics. It doesn't even
have a significant effect on any kind of
astronomical physics. Uh by astronomical
I mean things smaller than the entire
universe. In fact, for whatever reason,
this number happens to be such that it
only that this force only becomes
significant and comparable to other
forces at something like the radius of
the entire universe. So that it only
becomes important under those
circumstances. People who want to tap
the vacuum energy to get vacuum energy
to do work and as as a solution to the
energy
crisis have to deal with the fact that
if they wanted to get a tank full of
gasoline, they would have to extract the
energy out of a volume something like
the orbit of the moon or something like
that. So there's not a lot of energy
there. Yeah. And no way to tap it, but
That would that suggest that dark energy
is really a relative energy? Relative to
what? What does it
mean? Let's uh let let's let's
um I'm not sure what you mean by a
relative
energy. Do you
mean Well, it
gravitates. It gravitates. It has a it
has the effect of a distribution of mass
in the universe. So it's I'm not
uh you mean are only differences of it
important? Is that what you
meant? I'm not sure what relative how
relative was being used. I'd have to
yeah try to elaborate on that probably.
Yeah, it's probably
I heard that there's someone said
there's no particle associated with dark
energy like they don't really. No no not
with dark energy. Dark energy does not
have the form of uh any energy that's
associated with particles. We'll come to
it. I hope we'll come to it um in the
course of these lectures. But no,
there's no particles. Now, dark energy
is to be contrasted with what's called
dark
matter. Dark matter is an entirely
different thing, a totally different
thing. And it really is made up out of
particles, or at least it's believed to
really be made up out of particles. But
um this is not where I was going
tonight. I just uh I just uh wanted to
uh for those who were involved in these
exchanges of
email, I thought I would give you my
view of
it. Let's come back to the Newtonian
laws of
gravity. We need to spend a little more
time with Newton before we can move on
to Einstein. And when I say Newton, of
course, many of the things I'm going to
say Newton might not have really
recognized, but they are forms of uh or
expressions of Newtonian physics. First,
a little bit of mathematics, and it's
not really
mathematics. It's just um formalism, uh
ways of expressing equations,
symbols. All right. First of all, I told
you last time we used the symbol dell
last time. It's called
dell upside down delta and it's thought
of as a kind of vector but it's not
really a vector with uh definite
magnitude and definite
directions it stands just like every
vector if I wrote any vector over here v
we could say that's the same thing as
giving its
components the x component the y
component and the z component
So one way of viewing a vector is just
that it stands for three numbers. The x,
y, and z components of v could be a
velocity for example. Okay. The symbol
dell with an arrow above it stands also
for three
objects. But those three objects are
really derivatives. derivative with
respect to x, derivative with respect to
y, and derivative with respect to
z. So whenever you see a dell, it always
means you're differentiating something.
You're always doing a derivative of some
kind, a partial derivative or a set of
partial derivatives of
um of something. Now, for example, how
do you use it? It's really called a
differential operator. It's not a set of
numbers. It's a set of
operations. But it also has three
components. So let's say let me the
first
example the operation dell if it acts on
a scalar. Now a scalar just means a
function of
position function of x, y, and z. I'll
stop writing x, y, and z soon enough and
just call it x. But take a function of
x, y and z and apply to it the operation
dell. What does it make? It makes a
vector. Phi is not a vector. But dell *
phi is a vector. And what are the
components of the vector? The components
of the vector are
just derivative of phi with respect to
x, derivative of phi with respect to y,
and derivative of phi with respect to z.
So it creates a vector from a scalar.
That's one example of the use of dell.
Another
example supposing it acts on a vector
field. It can also act on a vector
field. What does it mean? Let's take
dell do a let a be let's let's use
v dell dov that's called the divergence
of v. We talked about it last time but
just to give you a little more feel for
how the symbols are
used. Dot stands for dotproduct. If I
have two vectors, let's call one W for a
moment. Let's call one of them W and
let's call the other one V. And I take
the dotproduct of the two vectors. What
it stands
for stands for the x component of W
times the X component of V plus the Y
component of W times the Y component of
V plus the third term which is similar.
That's the meaning of W dov the standard
old-fashioned dotproduct between vectors
which most of you have seen. All right.
By the
same
rule, we simply pref we simply pretend
that the symbol dell stands for a
vector. It's like w, but it's not a it's
not a real vector. It's just a set of
operations. And what this
gives is the derivative of vx with
respect to
x plus the derivative of vy with respect
to
y plus the derivative of vz with respect
z. In other words, it has the same form
except replace w by this set of
derivative operators. And so it's a neat
notation.
It's a notational device for doing
certain kinds of derivatives, partial
derivatives on various kinds of things.
Now, if phi is a scalar, then delfi is a
vector. What if v is a vector? What is
dell
dov? It's a scalar. In the same way that
the dotproduct between two vectors is a
scalar, the divergence of a vector is a
vector. These notations are pervasive
throughout all of physics, electricity,
magnetism,
uh, gravity and without them we would uh
we would not be able to we wouldn't be
able to function very
well. Okay, that uh that's just a
preliminary warm-up and definition. It's
really just definition. There's not any
deep mathematics. The deep mathematics
is of course in the notion of a
derivative or partial derivative.
Derivative along a
direction.
Now
I mentioned of course that phi here is a
function of position. A function of
position like that is called a scalar
field. It's a scalar and it depends on
position. depending on position like
that makes it a field. V the components
of V may also
be functions of position and in that
case V is called a vector field. All
right. So anything which depends on
position is called a field and that's
our basic
notation. All right let's come to the
field to the gravitational field. The
gravitational field is a property at
every point of space and let me define
this for you. It it first of all let's
imagine that it's created by some
masses. So let's imagine some masses
some mass
points and I'll label them as usual I J
K where I J and K run from one to
whatever. And let's call this over here
the E mass. Now what we do to define the
gravitational field is we invent another
mass. We imagine one more mass which
we'll call the test mass. The test mass
is a little tiny mass that we move
around in space and we examine the
forces on it and in terms of the forces
on it in different places in space we
define a field and that field is a force
field or strictly speaking a field of
acceleration. So here's what we do. We
take our little test mass and we hold it
and we let it go and we see how much
acceleration it accelerates with and in
what direction. Acceleration is a
vector. It has a direction. It has a
magnitude. And that
acceleration, the
acceleration experienced, let's draw a
little test mass. The test mass I'll
just draw with a little cross in it
there. All right. It may or may not be
real. It may just be in our imagination
or it may be a very small little mass
that we move around and explore the
vicinity of the real masses. And that
acceleration is a
vector. It depends on position. And I'm
not going to write x, y, and z now. I'll
just write x. x now standing for x, y,
and z. That acceleration. And let me
write it down for you.
Let's call the
vector from the E mass to the test mass.
The vector pointing from the E mass to
the test mass. Let's call that R
subi. Last time I had defined the vector
as the vector from the test mass to
I. Now I'm defining it to go from I to
the test mass. Those two vectors are
equal and opposite to each other. But by
defining the vector R subi as the vector
from I to the test mass, I will save
myself a minus
sign. Which
direction? Ah,
sorry. I think I want I want it to go
the other way. If I want to save myself
the minus sign, I want to make it go the
other way.
Yeah, R I goes that way from the test
mass to the particle which is creating
the gravitational field. Now, which way
is the force on this object? Due to the
E
mass, it's pointing toward the E mass,
right? The gravitational force on the
test mass is pulling toward the E mass.
And so, it's along the vector R subi,
not opposite to it. And that will save
me having to write a negative
sign. All right. So now what do we know
about this field of
acceleration? Well, it gets a
contribution from every test from every
real mass here. And the contribution in
particular from the E mass. It's a
sum. A is a sum over all the
masses. A sum over all the real masses.
It depends on the gravitational coupling
constant on Newton's
constant. It depends on the distance
from the test mass to R. That's R
subi
from R subi
squared. And what else? And it depends
on the
mass of the E particle.
Each particle has a
mass. The acceleration on this particle
due to the i particle is proportional to
the mass. It's proportional to g and
it's divided by r sub i^ 2. But
everything that's written here. None of
the things that are written here are
vectors. G is a number. M is a number.
And r r is the length of a vector. It
square is just a number. There's no
vectors on the right hand side. So
there's got to be something wrong with
this equation.
What's wrong is I have to remind myself
what direction the acceleration is and
it's along the direction R
subi.
So the way to deal with that is to put
another
R vector here. But then we have too many
Rs in the numerator. We have to put
another one in the denominator.
We have to make this
cubed because the length of this is r.
Another way to think about it is to
leave it as r
squared and think of this as a unit
vector. The symbol for a unit vector, a
vector of unit length is a vector with a
little hat on top of it. Little hat on
top of it means unit vector. A vector of
unit length. All right. So this vector
here is a vector. It tells you the
direction of things. It tells you the
direction of the
acceleration. But the magnitude of it
all comes from here. And we add them all
up. The acceleration on a test mass is a
sum of vectors all different uh
contributions. This depends on position.
For example, the further away we take it
from the distribution of mass over here,
the smaller it is.
If we bring our test mass right up to
one of the particles here, there's a
great big force on it. If we bring it on
the other side, the direction switches.
So this A here is a field. It depends on
position, and it's called the
gravitational
field. All right. There's a way to
summarize
this, which is neat. We talked about it
last time. I'm not telling you anything
I didn't tell you about last time, but
um the way to summarize
it is in terms of the
divergence of
a. Let's look at the
uh dell do
a that's the divergence of a and let's
look at let's just take the simple case.
The simple case, let's suppose there's
only one mass
point. If there's one mass point here,
then let's look at the gravitational
field in the neighborhood of that mass
point. Well, it's pointing inward. If I
take my mass, if I take my test mass and
move it around in the vicinity of the of
the uh of the heavy mass here, I'll
discover a gravitational field which
varies from point to point, always
pointing toward that mass.
Right? So the gravitational field the
vector field points inward toward that
point. The pointing the inward
pointingness of it is called the
divergence of the field. The divergence
of the acceleration field here is due to
masses and it's
proportional to the mass at every point.
There's a divergence which is
proportional to the amount of mass at
that point. To express it
mathematically, we have to invent a
concept called mass density. Now, we all
know what we mean by mass density. It's
not a new concept for most of you. Mass
density simply means uh take a volume of
space ask how much mass we're now
imagining that either that the mass is
continuously distributed not in the form
of point particles or that there are so
many point particles tiny tiny point
particles that we might as well
effectively think of it as being
distributed. Then the amount of mass in
a unit volume or the amount of mass per
unit volume is called
row
equals mass per volume. We take a small
m we take a small volume count up all
the mass in it. Delta m over delta v is
called is called the uh uh the mass
density the mass per unit volume. And of
course it varies in general from place
to place. Here there's no mass per unit
volume. Here there's mass per unit
volume. So the mass per unit volume is
itself a field. It's the density field.
Right? On the left hand side here we
have the divergence of A. The divergence
of A. A is a vector field but its
divergence is a scalar.
The relationship between masses and
gravitational field which is basically
the relationship that uh that Newton
wrote down here it is can be reexpressed
in the form that del do a is equal to
minus 4 pi I'll tell you in a moment
I'll remind you where the 4 pi comes
from why it's there times the mass
density oops times Newton's constant
The strength of gravity is always
proportional to Newton's constant. So
the effect of a mass is always
proportional to Newton's constant. It's
proportional to the amount of mass.
That's the row. And this is the basic
equation that you can think of as a
field equation. It relates two fields.
The field of acceleration to the field
of mass density. and the constant G is
just a constant in the
relationship. This is called Gaus's
law. Why is there a minus sign here?
Incidentally, well, the minus sign
simply takes into account that if you
have a mass point there, the
acceleration field is pointing inward.
So, you don't really have a divergence.
You have a convergence of the uh of the
gravitational field. But a convergence
is just a negative divergence. So that's
why the negative sign is there. Right?
This is called Gaus's
law. But there's another thing which is
named after Gaus and it's Gaus's
theorem. This is a law of nature. This
is equivalent to Newton's uh
relationship between the acceleration
field and the mass densities. It's
something that you get from experiment
or if not well from experiment or
observation. But there's a mathematical
theorem which is Gaus's theorem which
also has to do with divergences of
vectors. So let me remind you about
Gaus's
theorem. It is so central to everything
in
uh and certainly in gravity theory that
I feel justified in spending another 15
minutes on it or 10 minutes on it.
Um Gaus's theorem says that if you have
a if you have a field which has a
divergence that divergence is a scalar
and you take some region of space any
region of space that has a
boundary. It could be a sphere doesn't
have to be a sphere. It could be a
sphere with two ears sticking out of it.
Uh it should have the topology of a
sphere. Other words, it shouldn't be a
donut, but it should not have holes in
it or anything like that. Even then,
it's okay. But let's just take it to uh
to be a chunk of space like
that. Then what Gaus's law says is that
if you
integrate the
divergence over the volume dx,
dydz inside the region, and how do you
do that? What does that mean? That means
you break up the region into little into
little cubes, threedimensional cubes.
You break it up into tiny
three-dimensional cubes. In each cube,
you take the divergence of a, you
multiply it by the volume of the little
cube, and you add them all up. Okay,
that's integrating the divergence of a
over the interior region here. What it
says or what Gaus's theorem
says is that that integral is equal to a
surface integral a sum over the surface.
So let's draw the surface here. Let's
draw a piece of the surface and also now
break up the surface the bounding
surface also into little squares, little
cells. All right? And in each
cell the field A has a component
perpendicular to the cell. It may also
have components in the directions
parallel to the surface. But A has a
direction perpendicular to the surface.
Let's call that a
perpendicular or a sticking the
component of A sticking out of the
surface.
It says that Gaus's theorem says that
the integral of the divergence of a over
the
interior is
equal to the
integral over the
boundary. That's usually called d sigma.
Sigma stands for little surface area.
Stands for little surface here. The
integral d sigma of the component of a
sticking out of the surface. In other
words, it's just adding up all the
components of a sticking out of the
surface. The I I told you what the
significance of this would be for the
flow of water. If uh the divergence of a
stood for the divergence of the velocity
field of water, then it would just be
the amount of water being pumped into a
region here is equal to the amount going
out through the boundary. But this is
Gaus's theorem. Let's just isolate
Gauss's theorem. Now the integral over a
volume of the divergence of a is equal
to the integral of the over the surface
of the component of a
perpendicular. Now that's Gaus's
theorem. Now let's put them together.
Let's put them together to see how they
work together.
Let's imagine first that we have a
distribution of
mass which is spherically symmetric.
That means it doesn't have any
dependence on angle in space. Uh that
the distribution of mass has the
symmetry of a sphere. Symmetry of
rotational invariance. In other word,
there's another word for having symmetry
of a sphere. Anybody know what it
is? It's isotropic. Isotropic means the
same in every direction about a c about
a central point here. Okay. All right.
So, uh it could be a ball of material,
but it doesn't have to be a solid ball
of material, but it should be shaped
like a sphere. Okay. So, we have some
mass in here, and I want to know what
its gravitational field is. What I do is
I surround it nice and spherically,
symmetrically, concentrically with a
sphere.
I apologize for the fact that my
drawings are two-dimensional. If I had
some way to make them three-dimensional,
I would, but I can't. Uh, so they're
two-dimensional versions of surrounding
a spherically sym symmetric distribution
of material by a shell, by an imaginary
mathematical shell. Can the red be
seen? All right. So, there's a red shell
around here. Now, let's see what this
says. All right. First of all, we
integrate up dell do a. But what is da
a? From Gaus's law, not from Gaus's
theorem, but from Gaus's law, we know
that dell do a 4 pi - 4
pi times the mass density time g. So
let's work that out. So we're going to
get we're going to get minus 4
pi. We're going to get g.
And then we're going to get the
integral of the mass
density over the interior of the
sphere. The minus 4 pi g can come on the
outside of the integral since it's only
a constant. And the integral itself just
gives us this integral is just what you
see here. Now what's the integral of row
over over volume?
That's the mass. Integrating up the mass
density just gives you the mass
enclosed. So the mass enclosed within
the red sphere. Okay, so let's rewrite
that. That's
minus 4 pi g times the mass within the
sphere. If the sphere if the red sphere
is bigger than let's call this a planet.
Let's call it the planet. If the red
sphere is bigger than the planet, then
it's the entire mass of the planet in
there. -4 pi mg or -4 pi g. M is the
left hand side. What about the right
hand side of the equation? The right
hand side of the
equation says take the perpendicular
component of the acceleration of the
gravitational field. Now if the mass
distribution is isotropic the
gravitational field will also be gravit
be isotropic. In other words the
component the perpendicular component of
the field will be the same
everywhere. It'll be pointing out with
the
same component everywhere's on the
sphere. So that means that the
perpendicular component of a doesn't
vary from point to point on the sphere.
And that means that this integral here
is just the perpendicular
component whatever it happens to be
times the integral of d sigma. What does
the integral of d sigma mean?
It's just the area of the sphere. It's
just adding up all the little area cells
of the sphere. And that's the area of
the sphere which is 4
pi r
squared. R here not being the radius of
a planet but being the distance from the
center of the planet to the red
sphere. Okay. So now you see why the 4
pi was in Gaus's law. Why Gaus put it
into his law. It was in order to be able
to cancel that out at this point.
It was arbitrary. You could have defined
things
differently.
Now we solve this for the gravitational
field. And what does it tell us? It
tells us that the gravitational field of
a mass is minus mg over r
squared. Something we already knew.
That's Newton's law. that the
acceleration due to a massive object is
ma the mass of the mass of the object
times g / r 2. But it gives us a nice we
talked about this last time. I'm just
going back over it. It also tells us
that it doesn't depend on the mass
having all been concentrated at a point.
All it depended on was the mass was
spherically symmetrically
distributed. Okay. So that's that's I
did this again to point out to you
that del a= -4 pi row g is
equivalent to a being the sum over all
the mass points of Newton's
characteristic expression for uh uh for
gravitational field. So that's cool,
huh? It's a nice way to express things.
This summarizes the very very
complicated equation on top of it. It
doesn't look so complicated, but if you
wrote it out for lots of mass points and
so forth, it would become complicated.
Whereas, here's a way to express it
where it's rather
simple.
Uh yeah. Um, while we're at it, somebody
asked me last time about the
gravitational field within the surf
within the Earth. What is it like within
the Earth? Here we did the gravitational
field outside the Earth. We can now
carry out a calculation of what's going
on inside the Earth if we
like. It's kind of
interesting. All we have to do
now is take our red surface. Same
calculation but now take the red surface
inside the
earth. But now we have to be careful
because the amount of mass within the
red circle the red sphere is not the
total mass of the planet anymore. It's
only the mass within the red sphere. So
let's do the calculation over again. The
right hand side stays the same. The
right hand side is still 4 pi.
In other words, the uh the perpendicular
component of the field time 4 pi * r 2
where this r is now the radius of the
inner sphere
here. What about the mass within the red
sphere? How much mass is there within
the red sphere? Well, for that we we
have to make some kind of assumption
about how the mass is distributed
throughout the red sphere. Let's make
the assumption which is not so bad for
the earth. It's not a bad approximation
for the Earth that the mass density
within the Earth is
uniform. The mass density is uniform
inside the Earth and then when you get
to the surface of the Earth, it drops
abruptly to zero. That's not exactly
true. It's denser near the center than
near the outside. But let's take that as
a model. A uniform mass per unit volume
within
uh within the Earth. Then how much mass
is inside this red region here? It's not
the total mass of the earth. Now it's
different. So let's calculate it. It's
the volume of the sphere times the mass
density. Now this is equal to minus the
mass within the sphere. And the mass
within the sphere is the volume of the
sphere.
4/3 pi r
cubed. That's the volume of the sphere
time
row 4/3 pi r cub times row. I think I
got it
right. Oh,
uh on this side g good. Thank you.
All right, we can cancel out some
things. We can cancel out the four
pies. And now we can divide by r 2. If I
divide by r 2, what I get is a
perpendicular is equal to minus3
row * g 1/3 row * g time r.
What does this say? This says that the
acceleration of a test mass, of course,
we would have to drill a hole through
the earth if we wanted to drop a
particle. We can't drop particles if
they're stuck in the rock. But if we had
some sort of particle, well, either we
drill a hole through the earth and drop
particles down, or we drop particles
which don't interact with the uh with
the material of the earth. Nutrinos
don't interact much with the material of
the earth. We drop a particle. What does
it do? Well, it experiences an
acceleration which is toward the center.
That's the minus sign here. The
perpendicular component of A is
negative. That means it's toward the
center. It's got some constants in it.
Row, G, and three. Those are just
numbers. But it grows linearly with the
distance from the center of the Earth.
So, it's an acceleration, which means a
force. If I were to multiply this
acceleration by the mass of the test
particle on both sides, then I would
have the mass on the test particle. The
mass on the test particle is toward the
center and it's proportional to the
distance away from the center. Uh
there's a name for such a
system. It's a harmonic
oscillator. A force which is
proportional to distance. In other
words, a particle displaced from the
center will be pulled back to the center
exactly as if it were on a spring with a
spring
constant that depends on the mass
density, depends on the gravitational
constant, and it depends on
three. So, if we dropped a particle, if
we drilled a hole through the earth and
dropped a particle, it would just
oscillate up and down, up and down like
a harmonic oscillator. I forget the the
time constant. I think it takes about 10
minutes for it to go through the earth
and come back or something of that order
of magnitude.
Uh so and uh this is not important uh to
the general theory of relativity. It's
just another example of how to use
Gaus's law and Gaus's theorem to solve
what would be a very hard problem if we
had to add up the contribution of every
particle in the earth. I mean just think
about it. Uh how hard that would be. Yet
this uh yet this method allows us to uh
to do it
easily. Okay, any questions? Yeah. Is
there is there some reason why
the the distribution of the matter
outside of the the shell is negligible?
It's not just negligible, it's zero.
That's a good point. Okay. Um right, so
let's uh let's talk about this.
Yeah, that's right. That was one of the
consequences and one of the curious
consequences. I'm sure it gave Newton
some pause when he re when he realized
it, but that's right. It is only the
material inside the sphere which
contributes to the gravitational field.
The material on the outside all cancels
out. The gravity from here and the
gravity from here and the gravity from
here, they all cancel out. Newton
knew it and he proved it without
calculus which is quite a uh the reason
he proved all these things without
calculus is because none of his uh none
of his audience knew any
calculus and so he had to do everything
geometrically but uh we see it from
Gaus's law's law tells us among other
things that the gravitational field of a
spherically symmetric mass only depends
on the mass
within the radius R and doesn't depend
at all on the mass outside the radius of
R. A consequence of this, I think we
talked about it last time, but might as
well just say it again, is that if the
mass was entirely distributed on a
shell, imagine the mass was on a shell,
thin
shell, then inside the thin shell, there
would be no gravitational field at all.
Particles would move around as if there
was no gravity at all. On the other
hand, particles outside the shell would
see the gravitational field of the shell
exactly the same as if it were a point
at the center. So that's a rather
remarkable fact and it's special to the
1 / r 2 law. Notice that it tells you
assuming Gaus's law and Gaus's theorem,
you get the one over r 2 law.
I'm having a hard time equating those
two uh figures at the surface of the
earth. I get a four that I can't get rid
of. Oh, did I miss I may have missed a
four. Let's see where where
uh which uh where
should I go back? I need to go back a
step here. No, the expression there on
your right, the lower there. Yeah.
Equating that to the expression on the
board to your left at the surface of the
earth. Wait, wait. Left. this and this.
Well, those two gravitational
accelerations should be the same on the
surface. What should be the same as
what? A bar on the right board should be
the same as a perpendicular on the left
board at the surface of the earth. Oh,
at the surface of the good. Uh, did I
make a mistake? Did I lose a factor of
four somewhere? I may have left lost a
you miss. Is it a factor of four that's
missing? Four pi
from which one? Uh,
oh.
already cancelled the four pi in there.
Remember what? You're absolutely right.
They should agree at the surface of the
earth. Uh so someplace I lost the four
and a pie. But uh this one this one of
course is correct.
That's just Newton. Well, the mass you
cancel them because they're on both row.
One person. One person. Does somebody
see where I'm row with the mass? You
cancel the four pints cuz they're on
both sides of the equation.
Has to be function of the mass. One you
have row, one you have mass. So you have
to let me go let me go back and do it.
Uh okay.
All I hear is a buzz.
Oh, okay. One has row and one has mass.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Oh. Okay. No, it was
right. It was right.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. The
rel That's right. That's right. No. All
right. To the to those who didn't follow
the last discussion, forget it. It was
right. All right. One more concept which
is important before we get on to
relativity and the equivalence
principle. The equivalence principle in
particular is the idea of gravitational
potential. Just uh one one point the
gravitational field is a field of
acceleration. Yeah.
Is the grav if you have shell. Yeah. Is
gravitational field continuous or it
seems like no it jumps at the shell.
It jumps from it jumps at the shell. As
you go from outside the shell to inside
the shell, it jumps
discontinu discontinuous. The field
itself is discontinuous. Well, if the
shell has a finite thickness, if the
shell has a finite thickness, of course,
then it's smooth. But if the shell was
literally an infinitely thin shell, then
it
jumps, right? The gravitational field
jumps. Now the equation you had here
said that the gravit the force or the
acceleration varies linearly from the
center of the earth. Yeah. And yet you
until we get to the until we get to the
boundary of the earth. You also said
that the if we consider a series of
shells, the force on an object is all
the shells outside can be neglected and
all the shells inside, right? But the
the mass of a
subsphere is not linearly dependent on
the No, no, no. That's right. That's
right. We canceled out. Yeah. Okay. So,
let's let's go back.
No, let's go back. Let's go back. We had
on the left hand side, we have on the
left hand side of the equation the
gravitational field times the
area r
2. That was one side of the equation.
The other side of the equation had the
mass which you correctly say was
proportional to r
cubed. Divide by r 2 and we get a
proportional to
r. That's what we did. the r 2 the um
the area grows as r 2 the mass grows as
r cubed and therefore the gravitational
field is like 1 / r derive that equation
again which one the one that erased on
the board behind you
this one yes okay it's Gaus's law
again we take a
sphere which is smaller than the size of
the
Earth. Okay. One side of the Gaus's law
gives us the total mass within that
sphere. Is that clear clear? Who asked
the
question? Yeah. Is that clear? All
right. So, one side of the equation is
the mass within that sphere. What is
that? That's
4/3 pi r cubed times the density.
Well, we also have to throw in a
g.
Yeah. 4/3 pi r cubed time row is the
mass within that sphere and we multiply
it by g. That's one side of the Gaus's
equation here.
The other side of the Gaus's
equation is the integral of the
component of a sticking out from the
surface. That's equal to the surface
area
4 pi r 2 time a perpendicular and
there's a minus sign there.
So we have on the left side something
like r cubed on the right hand side r 2
I can cancel the 4 pi and then divide by
r. If I cancel the 4 pi, I get g over
3 r cub
row is
equal to minus r 2 a
perpendicular. And now divide by r
2. Dividing by r
2 leaves one power of r there. So it
tells me that the gravitational field is
linear just like a spring.
Okay. Now on the surface of the earth
you can equate that to mg / r 2.
Yeah. Okay. Mg is 4/3. M is 4/3 pi r. So
it's missing a 4 pi.
This one is missing a 4 pi. You're
missing the 4 pi multiplying g.
All I'm asking you to do is equate them
to see if they're easy.
It's got to be the volume times.
Think of row as the whole earth. No, I'm
looking at mass. The mass of the earth
is 4/3 rub
4/3 pi r cub* row. Right. Okay. So on on
one side you have 4/3 pi r cub you have
a 4 pi and on the other side you don't.
Is that good or bad? That's bad. Oh,
okay. I thought I did it carefully, but
maybe I made a mistake.
Let's take Let's take a vote. How many
think I'm right?
All right, let's let's do it. During the
break we'll uh uh during the break I'll
go through it with you and uh it is not
entirely possible that I make numerical
errors. It's how you get to m is by
doing the integral. Yes. That's where he
misses the fourth. Yeah. Yeah. So when
when you we'll we'll we'll work it out
in detail
uh during the
break. Okay. I was going to talk about
gravitational potential but I think I'll
do that next week. And I want to get on
to the equivalence principle. A little
bit of
um some new physics. This of course was
all old physics and it's taken us
another hour to uh to go through
Newtonian
mechanics. Just repetition of what we
did last time. But let's uh let's move
on now to the equivalence principle. Now
the equivalence principle of course is
the principle that says that a field of
acceleration is in a certain that
acceleration and gravity are the same
thing. But to make it specific
uh the elevator analogy is a good
analogy. Now for reasons that
are a little strange I'm going to have
my elevator accelerate horizontally.
It's just because I want to use the
coordinate and call it x instead of
y. Uh you'll see why. We'll we'll get to
it. All right. So, we have an
elevator. Somebody stands in the
elevator. I want to emphasize that this
has nothing to do with the uh with this
room. It could be in any direction that
the acceler that the elevator is
accelerating. It could be accelerating
by means of a cable or whatever rockets
I don't care whatever uh pulling it and
it's being pulled with an acceleration
let's call that acceleration little
g. What
about an object that's dropped by the
passenger within the
elevator? All right, that
object according to Newton's laws in a
frame of reference outside the elevator
in an inertial frame of reference
watching this that object stands still.
But what does it do relative to the uh
what does it do relative to the person
in the elevator? Well, the elevated
person gets accelerated that way with an
acceleration g, but he doesn't say he's
accelerated. He just says I'm standing
still. and he sees the little thing that
he dropped accelerate toward the floor
and of course accelerate toward the
floor with exactly the acceleration G,
but not toward the right. He sees it
accelerate toward the left. So he says
there's a field of acceleration inside
the elevator. There's an A field inside
the accelerator pointing
downward. Everything he drops gets
accelerated downward. exact downward
meaning to the left exactly as if
uh uh there was a gravitational field a
a field of acceleration pointing
pointing to the left. How big is it?
Well, it's just exactly equal in
magnitude to the acceleration that the
elevator is moving with little g. And so
he says there's an acceleration field of
strength g pointing toward the floor of
the elevator. Okay, looks like gravity,
sounds like gravity, smells like
gravity. Uh, the conclusion that
Einstein came to, and this you you might
say to yourself, why did it take
Einstein to say this? Almost any small
child who's been in an elevator would
have recognized it that
gravity, the effects of gravity, the
effects of gravity on everything that
this person does, juggles balls, does
whatever he wants to do is exactly
identical to what he would experience if
he were in an elevator being
accelerated. Gravity and acceleration
are the same thing according to
Einstein. In other words, the physical
effects of being in in an accelerated
elevator are identical to the effects of
gravity. Now, as I said, that seems
almost
trivial. I'll tell you what, let's take
a break and then come back to some some
discussion of its
non-triviality. Why Einstein was called
Einstein instead of uh Joe
Paluca. All right. So let's talk a
little bit about how
Einstein used this idea of gravity being
the same as
acceleration. He didn't just say that
but he used
it. And uh let's go through one
application of it and then start to
discuss uh some ideas about the general
theory of relativity.
So now let me put now uh let me return
to uh oh what oh oh before yeah before I
do that before I do that I there was
some reason why I put the elevator
horizontal. It had to do with a graph
that I want to draw.
Let's talk a little mathematically about
what it means to be in an accelerated
frame of reference. The accelerated
frame of reference was the
um was the frame of
reference as seen by the passenger in
the
elevator. His frame his or her frame of
reference. Okay.
So X is horizontal. That's why I had the
elevator going horizontally because I
wanted to use X and I want to plot X
along the horizontal axis and along the
vertical axis I'm going to plot time
T. This is all of spaceime X. Well, I
haven't plotted the other directions, y
and z, but time and x, and that's the
world inside uh inside and
outside. Now, let's first talk about
what it means for a frame of reference
to be uniform velocity. Before we get to
acceleration, let's just suppose the
elevator were moving with uniform
velocity, not accelerated.
Let's call the bottom of the accelerator
floor. Let's call that x prime equals
zero. In other words, we have two frames
of reference. Me standing on the outside
and I have a coordinate which I measure
by meter sticks and I might measure it
from right over
here. 1 meter, 2 m, 3 m, 4 meters and so
forth. All right. So that's my frame of
reference and I call my coordinate X.
And here are the ends of the meter
sticks. Meter
sticks. End of the first meter stick.
This is X. This is X= 0. X= 1. X= 2 and
so forth. All right. Now what about an
observer?
somebody in the elevator who's moving
with uniform velocity. He has his
coordinates. He stacks up his meter
sticks in here. His meter sticks are not
the same as my meter sticks. My meter
sticks are standing still in my frame.
His are moving in my frame. And he will
call the bottom the floor of the
elevator. He will call that x prime
equals zero. prime means in the frame of
reference of the uh passenger. Prime for
passenger. Okay, so there's also an x-
prime coordinate. Let's take x prime
equals zero. That's the floor of the
elevator. The floor of the elevator is
moving. And so the floor of the elevator
looks like that. As time goes on, the
floor of the elevator moves further and
further to the right. Not only does the
floor of the elevator, but x= 1 follows
along and x= 2 follow
along. Those were intended to be
parallel. I'm not sure they
are. So the moving frame of
reference measures distances relative to
the floor of the elevator over here.
Whereas the stationary frame of
reference measures distances relative to
x equals z over here. Now what's the
relationship between x and x prime?
Well, let's take an any old point over
here. This is a point in space and time.
It's a point of space at some time and
let's ask what its x value is. Its x
value is the distance to
here. In other words, it's the
coordinate that the stationary observer
sees. Just call it x.
What about x prime? x prime is the
distance to the floor of the elevator.
The elevator's moving. So x prime is
this
distance. What's the difference between
them? The difference between them is
just the distance that the elevator has
moved. Velocity of the elevator times
time. That's how far the elevator has
moved in an amount of time t. It's moved
with its velocity. It's moving with a
uniform velocity v * t. So what is x
prime? Here's x prime over
here. x prime is equal to x minus
vt. That's the relationship between the
primed coordinate and the unprimed
coordinate. And this you better get used
to this idea of relating frames of
reference like this.
Uh that's the relationship between the
moving frame and the stationary frame.
Now there's one other thing. In
Newtonian physics, we're not yet doing
relativity. In Newtonian physics, all
observers measure the same time. Time is
the same for everybody. And so we can
write another equation that t prime is
the same as t. This is Newtonian
physics. This is not yet relativity.
This is not yet Einstein. It gets
modified in Einstein. But this is the
relationship between the coordinates
measured by the moving observer and the
coordinates measured by the stationary
observer. It's a coordinate
transformation. X prime is X - VT. T
prime is equal to T.
Now what? Let's suppose now that there
was an object which is standing still in
the outside frame of
reference. This guy drops his ball here.
The ball stands, let's suppose it stand,
let's say it stands still in my frame of
reference just for fun. How does it move
in his frame of reference? Uh if it's
standing still in my frame of reference,
what is it doing in his frame of
reference? Uh I'm in particular
interested in the velocity in the
velocity. All right. So if a ball is
standing still in my frame of reference,
it means x is equal to a
constant. It's just standing there
still. The elevator is going by. The
person in the elevator is looking at the
ball. Sees it moving. All right. If x is
a constant, then x prime is of course
just minus vt. But what I want to do is
differentiate this equation with respect
to time. What does it say? It says that
x prime dot I'm using dot to indicate
time derivative. Standard notation we've
used it before. A dot indicates a
derivative with respect to
time. That's
equal to x dot. But if x is constant, if
it's standing still in my frame of
reference, that's zero. What's the
derivative of minus vt with respect to
uh
t?
just minus V. So this was a long- winded
way to say that the velocity of the ball
in the as seen from inside the elevator
is minus V. Of course it is. The object
was standing still in my frame of
reference. The observer is moving past
it with velocity V and of course sees it
moving backward relative to him with
velocity minus V. That's all this says.
Okay. What does it say about the
acceleration as seen in the moving frame
of reference? Let's differentiate it one
more time. Differentiating it one more
time, that gives us the acceleration in
the prime frame of
reference. What's the derivative with of
v with respect to t? If v is constant,
zero. So if it's not accelerating in my
frame of reference, it's not
accelerating in his frame of reference.
It's very simple.
Okay, trivial in fact. But now let's
suppose that the acceler the elevator is
not moving with uniform velocity but
that it's moving with uniform
acceleration then the distance that the
elevator moves is not vt. What is it?
Supposing it's moving with uniform
acceleration, a acceleration equals
little g, the acceleration due to
gravity.
Then how does the floor of the elevator
move relative to me if it's accelerating
like that? Well, it doesn't move on a
straight line. It moves on a curved
line.
It moves on a parabola. If it's
uniformly accelerated relative to me,
it's moving on a parabola. And that
parabola is
x= 1/2 g t^2. Is this known to
everybody? This is a uh a standard
formula for uniform
acceleration. Yell out if you don't know
it.
Okay, this is uh this is the elementary
calculation of a thing moving with
uniform acceleration. So the moving
observers the floor moves to the
right 1/2 gt^ squ along with a floor all
the other meter sticks the end of all
the meter sticks do the same thing they
accelerate off on a curved path in
spacetime and acceleration means a
curved path in spaceime so let's uh
let's see what the relation between x
prime and x is again same thing. Here's
x
prime. Here's x. What's the difference
between them? The difference between
them is x -
gt^2. This distance is 12
gt^2. The
distance from here to
here. x prime is x minus gt^2.
This is the new transformation for
transforming to an accelerated frame of
reference. Okay, let's say again that
the passenger drops a coin or whatever
it is and that the coin happens to be
standing still. He throws it in just
such a way that it's standing still in
my frame of reference. That again means
x is a
constant. What does it say about x
prime? It says that x prime well let's
let's work it out. Let's work it
out. What does it say about the
velocity if x is standing still and we
differentiate this? We get the
velocity in the prime frame of
reference zero from differentiating x
standing still in my frame of reference.
But what happens if we differentiate
minus 12 GT
^2 minus
GT? But I'm interested in the
acceleration that the observer in here
sees. So I differentiate it again. X
prime double dot. The acceleration seen
from inside here. What do I get when I
differentiate it once
more? Just minus G.
This is a mathematical
statement of the simple trivial
observation that acceleration works the
same way as gravity. The accelerated
elevator gives rise to an acceleration
for anything that you drop which is just
minus g just like in an ordinary
gravitational field of the earth.
So anything which is dropped in this
accelerator in this uh elevator
accelerates toward the floor not toward
not in the direction of the elevator's
acceleration but in the backward
direction that's the minus sign here and
it accelerates backward with the
acceleration minus g. Okay, so that's a
mathematical statement. But what I
wanted to bring out is that it really
has to do with using a set of curved
coordinates. It has to do or that
acceleration is really the choice of an
a curvy linear set of coordinates to
describe
spaceime. That's the real lesson here.
acceleration. An accelerated reference
frame is described by a coordinate
transformation to a set of curved
coordinates. Right? So we we need to
keep that in mind. The connection
between gravity and curvature we're
beginning to uh to
develop. But having done that, let's now
come back to some simple physics.
One of the things that Einstein became
instantly famous
for, we can work it out qualitatively.
It's the bending of
light. Okay. So he first his first step
was to say I really mean it when I say
that the laws of physics in a
gravitational field are the same as the
laws of physics in an accelerated
reference frame. and in particular not
just the laws of Newtonian mechanics but
the laws of everything. Nobody at that
time had the faintest idea how gravity
affects electric and magnetic fields.
They didn't know uh in fact I don't even
know that the question was asked at that
time in a serious way and so it wasn't
known for that reason it wasn't known
how gravity affects the motion of light
rays. What Einstein said is, I now know
how gravity should affect the motion of
light rays. So here's his elevator. Now
I'm drawing the elevator vertical. The
vertical the elevator will accelerate
upward. And let's suppose a light beam
is shined from one side to the other.
First suppose the elevator is not
accelerating. Let's suppose the
accelerator is stand the elevator is
standing still and you shine a light
beam. What does it do? It goes in a
straight line and it goes right across
the elevator. It hits this point over
here. Now, what happens if the elevator
is accelerated upward? Well, let's send
the light beam just arbitrarily. Let's
send the light beam at exactly the
instant when the elevator begins to
accelerate. It's not yet moving. It's
just beginning to accelerate. So, the
light beam starts moving off
horizontally. But now the accelerate
keep saying accelerate the elevator is
accelerating upward. And so where does
the light beam hit the other side of the
elevator? Down here somewhere and it
travels in a curved path. In fact that
curved path will be a parabola. Again,
it'll travel on a parabolic
orbit and that parabolic orbit
uh you can work out easily just from the
uh from the motion of the
elevator. And what do you find? You find
that the light ray has a downward
component of acceleration which is equal
to g. the same acceleration. If the
elevator is ele is accelerated
upward with acceleration g, then the
light ray will have a downward component
of acceleration which will also be
g. So by that little
argument nothing more than that Einstein
deduced the fact that light falls in a
gravitational field. As I said this was
unknown.
Nobody even suspected it that the
existence of heavy masses which create
gravitational fields would cause light
to do anything other than travel in a
straight line. In fact, light doesn't
travel in a straight line when it passes
uh through the earth passes across the
earth. Why? Because the gravitational
field of the earth can be thought of as
an upward acceleration. And so light
will
fall. Uh let's go through question.
Yeah. Suppose you shine the light in the
direction of the acceleration. Yeah. So
that it's a little more complicated.
It's still it's still uh it still has an
effect and it affects the energy of the
light ray. It won't affect the speed.
No, because that depends on right the
acceleration in the vertical direction
will correspond to change in energy of
the uh Yeah, it won't affect the speed.
That's correct. One more question. Yeah.
uh the the Edington experiment that
verified general relativity. Yeah. U if
you take plain old Newtonian mechanics
and assume that a photon is a particle
of mass e over c^² and just use Newton's
gravity equation, will it properly?
Yeah, let's do it. Let's do it. Let's
let's do it. Let's in fact that's
general relativity predicts exactly the
same thing by a factor of two.
But let's let's uh let's see if we can
roughly work out the bending of light by
the sun. Okay, the question is this. If
a light
ray passes the
sun and clearly Einstein has already
proved that light falls in a
gravitational field. So he wanted to
estimate this the first thing he did
before he had the full apparatus of the
general theory of relativity. He had as
much as I've explained up till now and
he said I will try to estimate how much
the light bends. In other words, what
angle does the uh does the light ray get
uh accelerate? What's the right word?
Deflected. Yeah. By what angle does the
light ray get deflected? All right. We
can make an estimate. Now at this point
he was reduced to estimates because uh
he didn't know the details of how the
spherical earth with its varying
gravitational field would really affect
things. But in particular he was
interested in a light ray which just
skimmed the surface of the sun got as
close to the sun. Why? Because the
effect would be maximal the closer the
light ray got to the sun. Of course he
wasn't interested in light rays that
went through the sun. Light rays don't
go through the sun. a light ray that
just barely skimmed the sun. Uh, how
much it got deflected. Okay, let's see
if we can figure it out.
Uh first of all in
passing in passing through
the when it passes close to the sun when
it passes close to the sun it has an
acceleration toward the sun which is
just the acceleration field of the sun.
So when it's in the vicinity of the sun
let's break it up. When it's when it's
out beyond the distance comparable to
the radius of the sun, it's too far from
the sun to feel anything. Whether it's
when it's within some region comparable
to twice the radius of the sun here, it
feels the gravitational pull of the sun,
right? What's the acceleration that it
feels downward? Well, for that we just
have to work out the acceleration due to
gravity. What we have to work out is how
much acceleration is there at the
surface of the sun. I think we already
had a formula for that, right? The
acceleration do is
um mass of the sun g over r
2. That's the uh do I have that right?
mg over r 2 downward. Right? Everything
gets accelerated downward. Light as well
as everything and all with the same
acceleration. So mg / r 2 is the
acceleration the vertical component of
the
acceleration
right how much
velocity does the how much vertical
component of the velocity now vertical
doesn't mean toward the sun it means
vertical on the blackboard here how much
vertical component of velocity does it
have after it passes the sun well to
calculate the change in velocity you
multiply the acceleration by time.
Acceleration times time is the change in
velocity. So you take this acceleration
and multiply it by the amount of time,
let's call it delta
t, that it takes for the light beam to
cross across the radius of the
sun. Now we can estimate that because we
know how fast light moves. It moves with
the speed of
light.
Uh so how long does it take? It takes a
time delta t which is approximately
twice the rate this distance here
divided by the
velocity. That's velocity time time
equals distance. So time is distance
that it travels divided by the velocity.
But what velocity? The velocity of
light. The velocity of light going
across here. So that's 2 R /
C. So let's plug that in. That gives us
another
two. The two is not
important.
R divided by C. And what is that? That's
twice
MG over R C. Right? That's the
downward component of velocity here. But
that's not the angle. The angle is
basically the ratio of if we have a
small angle relative to the horizontal.
Here's the horizontal. Small angle
relative to the
horizontal. That's the velocity. This is
the direction of the velocity after it
passes the sun. Then the downward
component here the the um the angle is
the ratio of the downward component to
the horizontal
component. The the downward component
divided by the horizontal component is
essentially the
angle at least if the angle is small. So
the angle let's call it
theta is equal to the ratio of the
downward component here it is 2
mg over
rc that's the downward component of the
velocity divide that by the horizontal
component of the velocity and that gives
you the angle another horizontal
component of the velocity is 1 / c and
here's the answer 2 mg / RC^
2 that's a very small angle typically
mainly because C is a big number and G
is a small
number. So G is a very small number. C
is a very big number. C^ squ is even
bigger and so that's typically a small
angle when the uh when the light ray
goes across the sun.
So that was the crude estimate that
Einstein
made. Um I can't remember what the what
the correct answer is from the general
theory of relativity. It's within a
factor of two of this. I think maybe
it's just exactly either twice this or
half of it. I can't remember.
Uh and so every light beam that passes
by the edge of the sun gets deflected by
that much. Right? That's uh that was
Einstein's prediction. It was verified
by looking uh at stars passing across
the sun during an eclipse. I won't we
don't need to go through that. Most of
you know the story. Uh but the main
point here is that Einstein used the
idea that gravity and acceleration are
the same. Something that was known to
everybody. But he used it in a context
which nobody had ever thought of. namely
he applied it to the motion of light and
to electromagnetic phenomena in
general. Okay. So that's
uh
now yes gravity is like
acceleration but that idea is pretty
much limited to a uniform gravitational
field a uniform vertical gravitational
field. It doesn't really make sense when
you try to think about it globally in
terms of the Earth's gravitational field
when you stop thinking of a flat earth
approximation. So here's the Earth.
The
effect of the Earth's gravity on
anything over here, out here, Einstein
said, is exactly the same as if you were
in an elevator over here accelerating
upward with uh with a certain
acceleration. Well, first of
all, you can the acceleration has to be
different in different
places, different direction in different
places, different magnitude in different
places. And so there's no overall sense
in which you can take the gravitational
field of the earth and replace it by a
single accelerated frame of reference.
The acceleration has to be this way over
here, this way over here, this way over
here, this way over here. So there's
certainly no sense in which the full
gravitational field of the earth can be
replaced by saying you're in an
accelerated reference frame.
What you can say is for a small amount
of time and over a small amount of
different distance distances which are
too small to detect the fact that the
gravitational field has different
directions in different places. In other
words, on a small elevator for a small
amount of
time, the effect of the Earth's
gravitational field is the same as the
effect of an accelerated elevator, but
only for a small amount of time. Why?
Because well unless you allow the
acceleration to change with time but for
a small amount of time you can pretend
that small amount of time and a small
amount of space not enough space to feel
the change in the direction of gravity.
You can say that gravity has the same
effect as acceleration. But if you
really think about it I mean you have to
think much more deeply about what the uh
what the gravitational field of the
whole round earth is. Now, this is
related to something
else. If you're freely falling near the
surface of the earth, you don't feel the
effect of
gravity. Uh you feel you can tell the
difference between freef fall and not
free fall, but there's no difference
between falling at the surface of the
earth and being at out in the middle of
space with no gravitating objects at
all. What
about what about somebody falling over
here? Can somebody falling falling over
here just in freef fall? Can they or can
they not tell the difference between
falling and being uh in an elevator so
to speak or being uh uniformly
accelerate? What's the right word? Uh,
can a person over here tell that they're
falling as opposed to being in outer
space? Can they tell the difference
between gravity and acceleration? And
the answer is yes. They can tell the
difference because the gravitational
field of the earth is not uniform. It
points in different directions and it
varies with distance. So that means an
observer, here's an observer, a cubic
observer, a cubic observer has a
different gravitational field on them in
different
places. The bottom of his feet is being
pulled harder than the top of his head.
So he's being stretched that way.
Uh the gravitational field is sort of
pinched in toward the center here and
there's some sense of being squeezed
this way. You know what those are
called? Those are tidal forces. We
talked about tidal forces last time.
Tidal forces are real. You can feel
them. But in order to feel them, you
have to be large enough to sense the
variation in the gravitational field. So
the right statement is if you're small
enough if you're small enough and for a
small enough amount of time then the
gravitational field you don't feel it in
falling and it can be completely
replaced by being in an accelerated
frame of reference. Gravity and
acceleration are the same. But if you're
big enough to feel the curvature of the
earth's surface and if you're big enough
and you wait long enough time and you
can feel the variation of the radial
component of the gravitational field
then you can definitely tell the
difference between being in outer space
and uh being in freef fall. Freefall
isn't so free. You get squished one way
stretched another way. These are tidal
forces. The effect of tidal forces are
an
obstruction to eliminating the
gravitational field by replacing it by
an accelerated frame of
reference. Right? You can't really
replace a gravitational field by an
accelerated frame of reference except
locally and over small times. So the
equivalence principle is a limited idea
that makes sense
only in this limited sense. Okay,
there's an obstruction to getting rid of
the gravitational field and replacing it
by free fall by um by a field of
acceleration and that obstruction is
tidal forces.
There's no way that you can construct an
accelerated frame of reference which
will completely get rid of the
gravitation the way that we would if the
gravitation were
uniform. Gravitation's uniform. You go
to an accelerated frame of reference
falling down with uniform acceleration
and gravity is gone in that frame of
reference. No way to do it for the real
Earth. The real earth is a gravitational
field which is created by mass and mass
corresponds to divergence of
gravitational field. It's the divergence
of the gravitational field which gets in
the way of trying to replace it by a
uniform acceleration.
So uniform
acceleration
is or how to say it
um eliminating gravity by replacing it
by a accelerated frame of reference.
There's an obstruction and the
obstruction is the masses in the
universe create a divergence of the
gravitational field.
Uh, I'm beginning to get tired, so I
think I should probably quit any minute
now.
[Music]
Um, we need to you need to review some
special theory of
relativity.
Perhaps I'll take another 10 minutes and
just remind you of the things we learned
about special relativity in previous
courses and which I want you to
know. Let's see.
Yeah.
Inside that elevator that's where
there's special relativity holes.
Exactly. Yeah. Lawrence transformation.
Yeah. We of course are studying it in
the approximation at the moment of
Newtonian physics.
Yeah, I don't think I want to do special
relativity tonight. I think I won't do
that. Instead, I want to talk about uh
geometry a little bit. Geometry
and curvature. Curvature is a concept
we're going to need. And I think we can
just um discuss it without discussing
physics for a little for a little bit.
How do I describe the geometry of this
blackboard? The geometry of this
blackboard is flat space. Just flat
two-dimensional space. Uh how do I
describe its geometry? The way a
mathematician would describe its
geometry is by specifying the distance
between any pair of neighboring points.
If you know the distance between any
pair of neighboring points, you can
rebuild the entire geometry from that.
Knowing the distance between any pair of
neighboring points, nearby points, is
enough to rebuild the geometry of this
blackboard. And to discover that it's
flat, let's take a pair of
points. Let's characterize them by
coordinates x and y, or just let's call
them x subi. i runs from 1 to two. And
here's another point at position x + dx
and y + dy.
two points separated by a differential
distance dx and dy. What's the diff?
What's the distance between them? The
distance between them is just dx 2 + d
y^2 or that's the square of the distance
between them. The square of the distance
between them, that's called ds squared,
is dx 2 + d y^2. That's just
Pythagoras's theorem.
dx
dy ds d s^ squ is dx2 + d
y^2. Now that is something which is true
if you use for your coordinates nice
rectangular cartisian coordinates.
What would happen if I replaced the
cartisian coordinates on the blackboard
by some crazy set of coordinates?
Coordinates for
which the axes were curved in some
highly complicated kind of way. There
are lots of different coordinate systems
that you can use to describe the
blackboard. They don't have to all be
drawn as a rectangular grid. We could
use polar coordinates. polar coordinates
look like
this. All kinds of other coordinates.
And in general, the lines of constant
coordinate, lines of constant x and
lines of constant y would be curves on
the blackboard. That would be a general
description of the blackboard, not tied
to nice
rectangular mesh like this. All right.
So let's suppose now this could be x =
1, x = 2, x = 3. Here's y and here's x =
0. Here's y = 1, y = 2, y =
3. I have a
grid. If I tell you the value of x and
y, you can tell me exactly where the
point is on the blackboard. But the grid
is no longer a rectangular grid. The
distance between two points is no longer
given by dx^2 by plus d
y^2. There's a general formula for any
kind of curved coordinates like this and
it looks like this. That's a ds
squared. Has some coefficients.
whatever it is, it will involve these
little differential displacements and
it'll involve them quadratically to the
second powers. We're going to go over
this again. I want to lay it out for
you. Now, we're going to even prove it,
but it's going to be some quadratic
form. This is called a quadratic
form. The x^2, dx * dy, and d y^2. It'll
have all of these things in it. And
furthermore, these G's will depend on
where you are. They'll be numbers.
They'll be numbers, but they'll really
be fields. They'll depend on X and
Y. X
X. I'm really getting uh tired, so I
should
probably quit in the next five
minutes. I don't know how many of you
have seen this for sort of formula. How
many have not seen it? How many have
not? All right. So, we're going to work
it out next time and I'll show you why
this is true. But before I do, let's
just go through what some of these
things
mean. What does it mean to have a g12
here? In the original formula, you had
nothing multiplying dx *
dy. There's dx² there's dy^ 2. I say
more generally, if you think about
general sets of coordinates with curvy
linear coordinates, then there'll be
terms with dx * dy. Do you know what
those mean?
When there's a term dx dy, it means the
coordinate axes are not
perpendicular. That's what that means.
What about g11 and g22? Those have to do
with the relative spread.
If we were to make coordinates like
this, which were much denser in one
direction than the other direction, then
the G11, the G22 would be different than
each other. If the coordinates curve and
things change from place to place, then
these G's depend on
position. But the general formula for
general curved coordinates for the
distance between two points looks
something like this. and it contains
three functions of position. G11, G12,
and
G22. Those functions are called the
metric. And we're going to go through
we're I'm going to show you why that's
true. But we're still just describing
the
blackboard. We're describing the
blackboard. And the blackboard could
always be described by these coordinates
here. When it's true that you can
describe a geometry in this simple way
like this, the geometry is called
flat. Even if you decide to describe it
in a more complicated way, if you can
find new coordinates that simplify it in
this form, it's called flat. This is the
hallmark of a flat geometry,
Pythagoras's theorem, if you
like. There are geometries which are not
flat. There are geometries that no
matter how you choose the
coordinates, you cannot reduce it to
this form. Those geometries are called
curved. You know example of curved
geometry, the surface of a
sphere. The surface of a sphere, you
cannot choose coordinates on the surface
of the sphere which makes the distance
between points dx^2 + d y^2. It's always
going to be more complicated than that.
No matter how you choose the
coordinates. What about the surface of a
cylinder? Is the surface of a cylinder
curved? No, it's not. It's flat because
you can always choose exactly the same
coordinates that you would choose if you
unrolled it.
You can't unroll a sphere and spread it
out flat on a on a surface. But you can
spread out a cylinder and make it flat
on a surface. Cylinder is flat. A sphere
is not. How about uh let's see what
other kind of um a saddle
surface. A saddle surface shaped like a
saddle is also not flat. Can't be
flattened out.
Uh a cone. Ah, what about a cone?
Hm.
Yeah, a cone is flat everywhere except
at the
tip. A cone is flat everywhere except at
the tip because you can always take a
cone. There's a cone.
Right. There's a cone at the tip.
Something's funny is going on. But
anywhere else you can unwrap it and
spread it out on the table. So you can
use coordinates on a cone except for the
tip which look like this. Cones are not
flat but only at the tip. Cylinders are
flat. Planes are flat. Spheres are not
flat. How do you tell what's a surface
or a given metric like this describe
something flat or not?
Well, the answer is curvature, which I
haven't defined. We're going to define
it. The answer is curvature. But
curvature is the
obstruction to flattening out the
coordinates. Tidal forces are the
obstruction to get getting rid of the
gravitational field by changing
coordinates to accelerated reference
frames. Though that connection is not
accidental.
Curvature is the obstruction to
flattening a surface out or to thinking
of it as
flat. Tidal forces are the obstruction
to removing a gravitational field by
coordinate transformation to an
accelerated frame of reference.
Uh that's the connection we want to
build up. That curvature of space and
time is essentially the same thing as
the effect of a real gravitational
field. The real effects of gravitational
fields are tidal forces. And that's what
we're going to find. That curvature of
spaceime is the same as tidal forces.
Okay, let's quit now before I fall over
uh in exhaustion.
[Music]
The preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.